<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-04-30T00:22:24+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Rational Mind</title><subtitle>Semper ad meilora</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Civil, Moral, and Spiritual Good</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/morality/2023/04/29/civil-moral-and-spiritual/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Civil, Moral, and Spiritual Good" /><published>2023-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/morality/2023/04/29/civil-moral-and-spiritual</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/morality/2023/04/29/civil-moral-and-spiritual/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1589994965851-a8f479c573a9?ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1740&amp;q=80" alt="Lady Justice" title="Lady Justice" />
Some people say there is no need for religion because everyone knows what is moral. This perspective, while seemingly true, is flawed. Let’s explore why with the following topic: Civil, Moral, and Spiritual Good</p>

<h2 id="civil-good">Civil Good:</h2>

<p>This is the level of laws, statutes, instructions, taboos, etc. Good deeds done on this level are usually done to avoid punishment. For instance, stealing will get one arrested, so one does not steal. This is the lowest form of good. Below this level, man is sinking into depravity. Good deeds on this level alone are inherently dead because they are done only to avoid negative consequences. A person who acts on this level alone is called a civil man</p>

<h2 id="moral-good">Moral Good:</h2>

<p>Virtues like hard work, integrity, kindness, etc. are usually not enforceable in any justice system but are beneficial to society. Everyone, with some thought, can see this. This is the realm of moral good or rational good, since it can also be thought of as what is reasonable.</p>

<p>However, hidden within this good are the motives from which one operates. The motives for these virtuous acts may be entirely self-serving, not necessarily for the goodness itself — which is usually the case because what is called good on this level is highly subjective. A person who acts on this level alone is called a moral man</p>

<h2 id="spiritual-good">Spiritual good</h2>

<p>This is good done on account of selfless love: love for the Lord and Love for the neighbour, or what is the same, love for the greater good. On this level, we do what is right because it is beneficial to the commonwealth of society, thus in line with God’s will. A person acting on this level is a spiritual man.</p>

<p>Outwardly, spiritual good is not different from civil and moral good, but inwardly it is entirely different. Also, moral and civic good are dead works (Hebrews 6:1) if they are not enlivened by spiritual good.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1518398046578-8cca57782e17?ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1740&amp;q=80" alt="Seeking human kindness" title="Seeking human kindness B&amp;W" /></p>

<h2 id="morality-can-be-used-as-a-means-to-serve-our-own-selfish-ends">Morality can be used as a means to serve our own selfish ends</h2>

<p>As humans, we are usually self-centred, and we usually act in line with self-benefitting motives. While this may not be entirely bad, it usually has negative consequences in the long run. Think of shady politicians running for office. They make all the promises, extol their virtues, and perform acts of service in a show of humility and readiness to serve, but when they’re voted into power — when it really matters — they have nothing to offer. Even when they act, it is for their own benefit.</p>

<p>Morality can be used to serve our own selfish ends. When operating on the level of moral goodness alone, we tend to brag about it; we seek honour and favour for it; we look down on others because of it; we virtue signal, etc (Luke 18:10-14). This is why morality alone is not enough: it can be done from a self-centred viewpoint, seeking only what we can get in return. Spiritual good, however, is done for what is beyond ourselves: the common, useful good.</p>

<h2 id="hypocrites">”Hypocrites”</h2>

<p>There are many places in the Bible where God warns us about these dead works. In Matthew chapter 6, The Bible talks about those who do their acts of righteousness for everyone to see. They are rebuked as hypocrites who seek the honour of men. In Isaiah 64:5, Bible talks about “him who rejoices and does righteousness, Who remembers You (God) in your ways”, as against people who have all sinned and whose righteousnesses are as filthy rags in verse 6. God draws near to the former and the latter He does not because their righteousnesses are filled with iniquity. As mentioned earlier, morality can be used to seek our own selfish ends or exalt ourselves above others. This the Lord doesn’t want.</p>

<h2 id="the-fear-of-the-lord-is-the-beginning-of-wisdom">The Fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom</h2>

<p>As we begin to seek the Lord’s will in determining what the right thing to do is, he opens our minds to what is truly useful and good in every situation. This wisdom is the basis of spirituality (spiritual good), the rock on which one’s house is built. (Matthew 7:24-25)</p>

<h2 id="takeaway">Takeaway</h2>

<p>We usually move from one stage to the next in our spiritual development. As children, we usually operate on the first level (civil good). As teenagers and early adults, we usually operate on the second level (moral good), and as adults, the final (spiritual good). But life is not perfect, and we find that even as adults we’re usually acting only on the lower levels. However, what God wants is for us to operate from the highest level: spiritual good. This way, our spiritual good will flow into our moral and civil states and edify them. It’s a step-by-step growth process through which He is constantly guiding and providing for us.</p>

<h2 id="further-reading">Further reading:</h2>

<p>Pure works Psalm 119:9, 1John 3:3, 1Peter 1:16 and 22, Luke 6:46, 2Timothy 2:21-22, James 4:8, John 15:4</p>

<p>hypocritical works: Matthew 23:13-23 and verse 27-28, 1 John 4:20, Matthew 6:1-4, Luke 20:46-47, Matthew 15:7-9</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Morality" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some people say there is no need for religion because everyone knows what is moral. This perspective, while seemingly true, is flawed. Let’s explore why with the following topic: Civil, Moral, and Spiritual Good]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spiritual Growth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/providence/2023/01/28/growth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spiritual Growth" /><published>2023-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/providence/2023/01/28/growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/providence/2023/01/28/growth/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1535231540604-72e8fbaf8cdb?ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1748&amp;q=80" alt="Butterfly chrysalises" title="Hangin butterlfy Chrysalises" /></p>

<p>Spritual GROWTH is integral to the human experience. It is through this that the Lord raises us. The natural process of natural growth (birth - death) mimics our spiritual development process. For this reason an adult behaving like a child is referred to as being immature. But why do we have to go through this process? Why aren’t we born with all the knowledge required for life? Why is it that animals, to whom we are superior, have all the knowledge –spectacular in most cases– required to live their lives? Let’s explore.</p>

<p>Unlike humans, animals are born into their perfect order: they come packaged with all the knowledge they need for their existence (nourishment, shelter, safety, reproduction, etc). For example, early in their lifecycles, butterflies make a protective covering (chrysalis) around themselves while they develop into adult butterflies with wings to fly. This is done without any supervision from a parent or peer. Beavers build dams to block streams of water in order to protect themselves from predators. All this is possible because animals do not have a rational faculty. In other words, they cannot reason about their life choices. Everything is done by instinct. They just do it. As such, a beaver will never corrupt the instructions required to be a beaver.</p>

<p>Humans, on the other hand, have the ability reason and the freedom to act in contrast to the order they were created in. For this reason, humans are born in complete ignorance. Through institutions such as families, schools, churches, etc., humans learn to take instructions necessary for GROWTH, so that they too can come into their order – a love for God and a love for the human race. The Lord provides this.</p>

<p>If humans were born into their perfect order, they would be conceited and will pervert that order into which they were born. This is because they would feel like a know-it-all, without need for instruction from God. The consequence of this is a deviation from God’s order and a determination of a new order for themselves – a destructive self-centered love. Challenges in life, thus, provide an opportunity to fallback unto the training they have received from these institutions, and GROW into the life for which they were ordained</p>

<p>This is how the Lord through his providence uses the GROWTH process to lead us, and it is why GROWTH is integral to our existence as humans</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Providence" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No Room in the Inn</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/providence/2022/12/24/no-room-in-the-inn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Room in the Inn" /><published>2022-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/providence/2022/12/24/no-room-in-the-inn</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/providence/2022/12/24/no-room-in-the-inn/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>“And she brought forth her firstborn son, and wrapped him in swaddling clothes, and laid him in a manger; because there was no room for them in the inn.” (Luke 2:7)
<img src="https://nornirn.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/no-room-at-the-inn.jpg" alt="Mary and Joseph at the inn" title="No room for christ's birth in the inn" /></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Christmas is an annual event commemorating the birth of Jesus Christ and is celebrated by billions of people around the world on December 25 (Wikipedia). The circumstances surrounding Christ’s birth are quite peculiar. On the surface, it looks like Christ avoiding high expectations and coming into the world in humility, but there’s more to it. In its depths, it’s a story of love, growth, and the role you have to play in extending the Lord’s reach to all mankind</p>

<h2 id="the-birth-of-christ">The Birth of Christ</h2>

<p>The birth of Christ, albeit a historic event, need not be seen as a one-time occurrence because the word of God is everlasting (Isaiah 40:8), and if it is everlasting, then it is applicable to our present lives.</p>

<p>The birth of Christ marks a stage in our spiritual journey where we feel God’s presence in a new way. In life, we face numerous difficulties, some of which can be daunting. However, these difficulties also present opportunities for the Lord to reveal himself to us in new ways. Our understanding of life is elevated as a result of this manifestation, and we go through life wanting to share God’s love with others and volunteering to serve others (Matthew 22:34-40). Such an experience is a depiction of Christ’s birth in us.</p>

<h2 id="no-room-in-the-inn">No Room In The Inn</h2>

<p>Inns, historically, were places for travellers to replenish (rest and refill with food and drink) before they continued their journey. Regarding our spiritual lives, inns represent the ideas, and activities that we rest on and refill with on our spiritual journey. As we sojourn through life, our spiritual states are continuously changing, so we also need spiritual inns to replenish.</p>

<p>The conditions surrounding the birth of Christ two thousand years ago were unfavourable for his physical birth. The Jews back then were misinterpreting and misapplying God’s word, turning the church of the Lord into a place of commerce, and doing many other things which were unpleasant in the sight of the Lord. In a similar manner, our current state of mind, the beliefs we hold, the knowledge we acquire, and the activities we are involved in could be unfavourable for his spiritual birth in our lives.  It’s not sheer coincidence that there wasn’t room for Christ’s birth in the inn. God always arranges everything in order, and what occurred then was just a snapshot representing the state of the church at the time.</p>

<p>As the Bible says in Ecclesiastes, there’s nothing new under the sun. Since the word of God is always applicable to our lives, we must ask ourselves, “What similar activities are we engaged in that are making our inns full?” Yes, life is difficult, and we might be in a bind at the moment, but does it excuse a misapplication of God’s word to justify our current deeds? If our deeds allow for the entrance of God’s leadership on how we conduct our lives, then we have room in our inn for Christ, and we can be sure of His deliverance, joy, hope, loving-kindness and peace. Otherwise, we have no room for Him in our inn.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>The birth of Christ in our lives is a tremendous opportunity for spiritual growth. During this festive season, many people will be travelling to see their families, or just to enjoy their vacations. Many will spend time in hotels, which are like modern-day inns. Yet, in our working hard to afford such vacations, in our day-to-day hustle, in the challenges we face, are we able to make room to feel God’s presence in newer, more uplifting ways? Are we making room in our inns?</p>

<p>Please share your thoughts and how you’ve experienced the birth of Christ in your life this year. We’d love to hear them.</p>

<p>Merry Christmas!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Providence" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“And she brought forth her firstborn son, and wrapped him in swaddling clothes, and laid him in a manger; because there was no room for them in the inn.” (Luke 2:7) Christmas is an annual event commemorating the birth of Jesus Christ and is celebrated by billions of people around the world on December 25 (Wikipedia). The circumstances surrounding Christ’s birth are quite peculiar. On the surface, it looks like Christ avoiding high expectations and coming into the world in humility, but there’s more to it. In its depths, it’s a story of love, growth, and the role you have to play in extending the Lord’s reach to all mankind]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unconditional Love. Part II (Romantic Relationships)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/love/2022/01/16/love-uncondition-part-II/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unconditional Love. Part II (Romantic Relationships)" /><published>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/love/2022/01/16/love-uncondition-part-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/love/2022/01/16/love-uncondition-part-II/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1513279922550-250c2129b13a?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=2070&amp;q=80" alt="Main Image" title=" Main Image" /></p>

<p>Modern relationships can, at times, feel more like contracts than actual love. A lot of the debate on the internet is about who brings what to a relationship, what is received for love shown, etc. The paradox here is that while we crave love in its most idealistic form (i.e pure and unconditional love), we choose love primarily based on what we will gain (power, status, money, excitement, personal value, etc.). Such an orientation leaves us overly concerned with conditions that must be present in and around a potential partner, yet none of these conditions matter for the longevity of romantic associations. Loving someone means we care about their well-being just as much as we care about our own, or even more. It may seem counterintuitive, but it is the only way to build sustainable relationships.</p>

<p>This post is a continuation of the previous one where we discussed unconditional love from a deistic point of view. In this second installment, — also drawn from a conversation with Pastor Jeffery Walter of Cafan Media —, we discuss what the principles of unconditional love in romantic
relationships are and why we must apply them. While the ideas expressed here are in the context of romantic associations, they can be applied to any kind of relationship.</p>

<p><img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/dbrrygmpk/image/upload/v1649893019/Screenshot_58_szfnhv.png" alt="Mark Manson Unconditional Love tweet" title="Mark Manson Unconditional love tweet" /></p>
<h2 id="the-discussion">The Discussion</h2>
<p>Q. Can Romantic Attachments be based on unconditional love?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A. Romantic attachments, in their beginning stages, are usually not true love. At this stage, our attraction to another person may be based on what we want for ourselves. A union forged out of this sort of attraction alone is self-centered, so the love from it will destroy itself if it continues this way. Suppose we are with someone only because of what we’ll gain. In that case, we’ll eventually discover that the person is not perfect. Ultimately, what we want from the person may not matter to us anymore, causing the love to become doused. However, this type of attraction can be a first step in bringing two people together.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>It is desirable that it moves on from this first state into unconditional love, where we love the person for the sake of the person. If we love someone for the sake of the person, then we are not motivated by what we get from that person, or what the person does, or our self-centered desires, but we are driven by the good we want for the person, so we do well towards the person.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Q. How does this play out in our relationships?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A.Unconditional love in relationships or in marriages is a bit different. In Unconditional love part 1, we learn that God is all-sufficient, so we do not give him anything. The only thing we can give God is how we allow Him to love us. However, in the marriage between two people, it is not enough for one person alone to give all the love; that makes the relationship one-sided.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Inasmuch as a person must focus on loving their partner, a secondary desire must go with it: adesire to receive love in return. This is the only way that oneness in marriage is attained. Anyone who wants the oneness of marriage should first love their spouse and wish that their spouse should love them in return. The order, however, must not be reversed. The primary love is what you have to give; it stands independently. The secondary love is what you receive in return. Secondary here means that it can be sacrificed for the primary. So even if your love is not met, the most important thing for you is to focus on loving your spouse (primary love). This kind of love is unconditional.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Q. So what happens when our love for another is not returned and there’s no union?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Love is revealed in what it seeks to achieve in a person and its quality is in its purpose. If someone you love decides that they no longer love you or is no longer interested, then the quality of the love you have for that person changes. It changes because the purpose of that love is no longer to the end of marriage or is no longer romantic in nature. The purpose now could be for friendship or for the sake of anything good other than marriage. The love, even though its purpose is changed, if unconditional, never dies.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="unconditional-love-is-a-must">Unconditional Love is a must</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Greater love hath no one than this, than to lay down one’s life for his friends….You did not choose me, but I chose you.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>— Jesus Christ</p>

<p>Developing a penchant for unconditional love can be challenging yet very rewarding. Aside from the
possibility of being able to feel another person’s joy as your own, – which is the greatest joy there is –
there are many other reasons for wanting to develop a tendency towards unconditional love.</p>

<h5 id="our-love-matures-as-a-result">Our love matures as a result.</h5>

<p>There are times when we claim we love others when in reality, the love we show is only a means of
getting something in return. As a result, we get very manipulative in relationships, and when things
don’t go our way, we get angry. This sort of behaviour leads to quarrels, arguments, fights, and even
murder in some instances.</p>

<p>Unconditional love demands that we develop a more outward-looking attitude when it comes to love,
focusing on the good things we can give without thoughts of recompense. In relating to other people
this way, we are challenged to look beyond their shortcomings (if possible), to learn to forgive, to let
things go, to be kinder and more caring. If we are loved in return, then there’s union. If not, our love
remains unsullied, and we’ve most likely become better people for it.</p>

<h5 id="it-helps-to-eliminate-the-negativity-and-ill-feelings-that-are-associated-with-love">It helps to eliminate the negativity and ill feelings that are associated with “love”:</h5>
<p>Have you ever loved someone and felt deep anxiety as a result? Maybe you thought if you didn’t do the right things at the right time, you’ll eventually miss out. On the flip side, you may “loved” someone and done so many things for this person who is the object of your love. If only this person reciprocated your love in the way you wanted, you would be fine.</p>

<p>Conditional love is predicated on what we will receive for the love we have shown. Since there is no guarantee that we will get it, we get anxious and emotionally unstable. This instability leads to all sorts of mental anguish. The alternative is to aim for our love to be constant regardless of what we get from this person. This is how we know we truly love someone, and it only comes when we set about to love that person unconditionally.</p>

<h2 id="another-fictitious-example">Another fictitious Example</h2>

<p>Since the triangle is the strongest shape, it will make for a great illustration of the concepts we’ve
discussed. The idea here is that, for any two people, the closer they get to unconditional love for each
other, the closer they get to each other. This concept will be demonstrated with a story about John
and Jane, with a focus on John.</p>

<p>John meets Jane and feels very attracted to her. Before he met Jane, he had a lot going on for
himself. He had everything under control, and everything he added to his life was added to increase
his joy. Now that he likes Jane, he applies the same principle: maximize gain; minimize pain. His
focus is still entirely on himself, though he claims he loves Jane. John doesn’t realize that Jane is a
human being full of her own emotions and personal desires, not an object to him happy.</p>

<p>Eventually, the relationship becomes one-sided. John only seems interested when he wants
something from Jane. At the same time, Jane cannot unite herself with John because her love for
John is only reciprocated when she does certain things. In time, John becomes a domineering force,
always dictating, and when things do not go his way, he looks elsewhere. John has missed the boat
on what it means to love someone, and this is what the state of their relationship looks like:</p>

<p><img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/dbrrygmpk/image/upload/v1645906606/unconditional_love_2_elnuqv.svg" alt="An image of two couple far apart from each other" title=" Spiderman pulling two halves of a splitting ferry together" /></p>

<p>In time, John comes to realize the error of his ways. He notices that his self-centeredness in chasing
his personal happiness, primarily, is creating a rift between Jane and himself. John has a change of
heart and decides to love Jane without setting demands on her. He decides to seek ways in which he
can be more useful or loving to her. As he does this, he notices a deeper connection to Jane with this
new approach to their relationship</p>

<p><img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/dbrrygmpk/image/upload/v1645906653/unconditional_love_4_dfgqyg.svg" alt="An image of two couple far apart from each other" title=" Spiderman pulling two halves of a splitting ferry together" /></p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>The hallmark of love is not loving ourselves but loving others and being united to others through love,</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Divine Love and Wisdom by Emanuel Swedenborg</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p>While having conditions is not a bad thing, it is only a preliminary stage of attraction, and we
should develop unconditional love out of this initial attraction. If we only care about what we’re
getting, then the other person is but a tool for us to seek selfish pleasure.</p>

<p>While this talk about unconditional love may sound idealistic, the concept is not alien to us. It is
something we are accustomed to in our relations with friends and family. In most of such cases, we
are not looking for what we stand to gain, so everything we do for them is from a genuine concern for
their well-being. With our romantic partners, however, we tend to expect more, causing a lot
complications.</p>

<p>Having dealt with the whats and whys of unconditional love, we can now turn to the hows. One huge
concern we have mostly is, how do we go about loving and caring for other people’s well-being in a
way that prevents them from taking advantage of us? It is a delicate balance, but it is achievable.
Obtaining this balance will be the subject of part III of the unconditional love series.</p>

<p>Until then, remember that there is more blessing in giving than receiving.</p>

<h3 id="additional-reources">Additional Reources</h3>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://markmanson.net/unconditional-love" title="Unconditional Love Mark Manson">Unconditional Love Mark Manson</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Love" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Modern relationships can, at times, feel more like contracts than actual love. A lot of the debate on the internet is about who brings what to a relationship, what is received for love shown, etc. The paradox here is that while we crave love in its most idealistic form (i.e pure and unconditional love), we choose love primarily based on what we will gain (power, status, money, excitement, personal value, etc.). Such an orientation leaves us overly concerned with conditions that must be present in and around a potential partner, yet none of these conditions matter for the longevity of romantic associations. Loving someone means we care about their well-being just as much as we care about our own, or even more. It may seem counterintuitive, but it is the only way to build sustainable relationships.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unconditional Love. Part I (Divine Origins)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/love/providence/2022/01/15/love-unconditional-part-I/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unconditional Love. Part I (Divine Origins)" /><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/love/providence/2022/01/15/love-unconditional-part-I</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/love/providence/2022/01/15/love-unconditional-part-I/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.pexels.com/photos/937465/pexels-photo-937465.jpeg?auto=compress&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;dpr=2&amp;h=650&amp;w=940&quot; Logo Title Text 1&quot;" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>Our idea of who God is pervades everything in our spiritual space and determines how we live our lives. For much human existence, there has been a challenge of understanding who or what God is, as humans have sought, through many different media, a path to God. In modern times, the preference for a proven scientific approach to solving our challenges has become prevalent, leading many to doubt the existence of a God, let alone one that is unconditionally loving.</p>

<p>Religion also sometimes, seemingly, offers no solace. Here, we are on occasion presented with a God (or gods) whose love is conditional. In the Old testament (Christian Bible), for instance, God said: “Thou shalt not bow down thyself to them, nor serve them: for I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children unto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me; And shewing mercy unto thousands of them that love me, and keep my commandments”. Yikes!</p>

<p>So how do we reconcile this idea of agape love with seeming conditional love set forth by our Deities? Here (on the rational mind), one of our goals is to understand things from first principles. In this post, mostly drawn from a conversation with  Pastor Jeffery Walter of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/CAFANMEDIA/about" title="Cafan Media">Cafan Media</a> about what unconditional love is, I outline what I believe is a sound model of unconditional love, and how an all-loving, all-wise God goes about loving his subjects.</p>

<h3 id="the-discussion">The Discussion</h3>

<p>Q. Why is it that God seemingly withdraws from us when we stray from his path? Doesn’t that make his love conditional?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A. God’s love is not conditional. God’s love is seemingly  waning or kindled depending on the individual’s perception.  Let me use the sun and planets as an example. The sun does not increase or reduce in its intensity. However, the earth, due to its position, receives this light and warmth in varying degrees. As a result, we have winters, summers, springs, autumns, days and nights. So this change in the position of the sun is only an apparent change. Likewise with God, the closer we move to him, the more intensely we feel his love.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Q. If I have to do something to get closer to God, isn’t this love still conditional on my part?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A. The idea of conditional love has to be looked at from its inception. If God is going to love you, do you motivate him to love you? No. If you do not motivate him to love you, then the love from its source is unconditional. This means that God loves people who are farthest away from him in the same way he loves the people who are closest to him. God’s love does not diminish towards anyone.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Those that are closest to God are those who have allowed God in.  In order to receive God’s love, one has to freely open his or her doors to allow the love in. Love that is not received freely is no more love, but domination, and God does not dominate anyone. So obeying God’s commandments is not a way of causing him to love us; rather, it is a way of opening the doors to receive his love. If I come to your house and you open the door, it does not mean that you made me come to your house. However, for my coming to your house to be effective to you, you must open the door and bid me in.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Q. How do I get closer to God then?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If we look at God’s commandments as something we must do in order to receive his love, then we will not benefit much from it because it will become burdensome to us. If we view God’s commandments like a parent guiding his or her child unto the right path, then we will be more willing to allow him to love us freely.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="wax-on-wax-off-an-illusory-example-spoilers-alert">Wax on; Wax off. An illusory example (Spoilers alert)</h3>

<p>Karate Kid is one of my all-time favourite movies. In the movie, Daniel LaRusso is being bullied by Johnny Lawrence, so Daniel goes to Mr. Miyagi to teach him some Karate so he can defend himself. To begin training, Mr. Miyagi gives Daniel a bunch of seemingly pointless exercises like, <a href="https://youtu.be/SMCsXl9SGgY" title="wax on; wax off">wax on; wax off</a>, where Daniel cleans old, dirty cars with an elaborate, swiping motion. In addition to this, Daniel is made to scrub floors, paint fences, among other things. Mr. Miyagi’s methods are eccentric, and Daniel is tempted to quit at a point; however, he will come to know the value inherent in these exercises later on, especially when he wins All-Valley Karate Championship.</p>

<p><img src="https://c.tenor.com/Wmayd_hVXv0AAAAd/karate-kid-wax-on.gif&quot; Wax On; Wax Off&quot;" alt="Wax on; Wax off gif" /></p>

<p>Ultimately, God’s desire is to bring us to place of genuine happiness. A lot of the happiness we seek for ourselves is mostly harmful. What God wants to do is rearrange these desires so that they align with orderly happiness: happiness that would not destroy us and the people around us. It is like Daniel LaRusso wanting to learn karate so that he can take revenge on Johnny and being told to wax on; wax off. Eventually, Daniel learns the self-discipline and self-mastery it takes to become a true karate master. These values will serve him well even beyond karate and play a role in making him a successful business owner ( in my opinion ). Daniel comes to love Mr. Miyagi so much, because of the training he received from him.  What does Mr. Miyagi get from all this? Nothing, but the selfless joy of seeing Daniel develop into his best possible self.</p>

<p>Of course, this example is a bit contrived. God is not trying to teach you karate, but the point here is this: God loves us so much, and all he cares about is bringing us to a place of genuine happiness. God has been moving in an infinite capacity from eternity for us. It is up to us to align ourselves.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Either you karate do yes, or karate do no. You karate do guess so, kwhee [squishing sound]. Just like grape. Understand?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>– Mr. Miyagi.</p>

<h3 id="takeaway">Takeaway</h3>

<p>The takeaway here is this: God is constant, and that constant is unconditional love. Contrary to what you might read, think or hear, He is not a vengeful, tyrannical overlord whose goal is to bend our will to his purpose only. Given the challenges we face, it is difficult to see how this is true. There are times when we compel ourselves out of fear to draw closer to God. At other times, we get mad at God and shake our fists, yet it is love and understanding that imparts joy, not fear. Coming to this understanding does not happen overnight. It takes time, and it takes effort.</p>

<p>The best way (I’ve found) to understand unconditional love is to mimic it in our own lives because then we’ll begin to truly understand the joys inherent in living for a greater purpose. Here’s an exercise, pick one thing that you can do now that people, not just yourself, will benefit from. It doesn’t have to be the grandest thing like donating a lot of money. It could be the smallest of things like sweeping a room, or cooking a meal. The goal of this exercise is to be process-oriented, not outcome-oriented.  In other words, focus NOT on what you’ll get, but on producing your best work. There is, after all, more blessing in giving than in receiving. See it through, and journal how it makes you feel. It may or may not work for you, but you can send us an <a href="https://therationalmind.org/contact" title="email">email</a> of your experience with it. We eager to know whether or not it works for you.</p>

<p>Now, many (of my friends at least) have argued unconditional love is impossible for us mere mortals, but I don’t see it this way, so join me in the second part of this series, Love unconditional-Part II , where we explore how we can apply the ideas espoused here to our personal relationships and, possibly, love unconditionally.</p>

<p>Postscript: There are many things mentioned or alluded to in the article that weren’t expounded upon. For instance, we did talk about why there’s so much suffering in the world if God’s love for the human race in unconditional. These topics are deep and would require their own articles or article series to explore them properly.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Love" /><category term="Providence" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our idea of who God is pervades everything in our spiritual space and determines how we live our lives. For much human existence, there has been a challenge of understanding who or what God is, as humans have sought, through many different media, a path to God. In modern times, the preference for a proven scientific approach to solving our challenges has become prevalent, leading many to doubt the existence of a God, let alone one that is unconditionally loving.]]></summary></entry></feed>